Sina Rezazadeh Baghal

Linkedln

About Me

Email: siinabaghal@gmail.com Phone: 226-972-8891, Toronto, ON

I am a quantitative finance self-learner. My PhD was in numerical analysis, optimization, and machine learning methods. Later, during my internship at CMRM, CIBC, I had an invaluable exposure to quantitative finance which sparked my interest in the field. I started by reading Shreve's "Stochastic Calculus for Finance II" and have kept studying from other sources since. Also, I have 7 years of coding experience in Python and MATLAB (also familiar with C++), enjoy implementing algorithms and have work experience in neural network implementation (Pytorch).

Work Experience

Data Scientist II

TD (Full Time Permanent)

Toronto, CA

July 2023 - Present

- o **Delivery**: Data extract pulls in SAS and SQL (Oracle). Data analytics (e.g., ML algorithms) on transaction data. Data cleaning. Time sensitive ad-hoc projects.
- Technical Skills: Database programming in SQL and SAS , Oracle, Python

CIBC (Full Time Internship, 1 Year)

Toronto, CA

Aug 2022 - July 2023

Quantitative Analyst

- Delivery (FRTB IMA): Non-Modellable Risk Factor Time Series Construction: Developed tools and methodology for time series construction of credit derivative risk factors such as single-name CDS spreads, Sector CDS spreads, CDS Index Spreads and CDS Index Volatilities. Developed methodology to identify proxy/reduced-set time series. Developed OOP style Python package using bash scripting and parallel processing to handle large data and ensure maintainability
- o Technical Skills: Mathematical finance, FRTB, Python, Performance optimization, Parallel processing, OOP
- o Weakly Presentation: Applications of Graph Neural Networks in finance, Chapters 1&2 of Bergomi's SV book
- Self-Study¹: Studied topics include: stochastic calculus, risk-neutral pricing, BSM, pricing using PDEs, exotic options, American derivatives, term structure models (Vasicek, CIR, Hull-White, Forward LIBOR), volatility smile, volatility surface (Heston, SABR) calibration and credit risk. Last but not least, I authored solutions to exercises from Shreve's "Stochastic Calculus for Finance II". See my Learning Quantitative Finance page for details.

Huawei Noah's Ark Lab (Full Time Internship, 6 Months)

Montreal, CA

Research in neural network quantization based on product team's requirements

Feb 2022 - Aug 2022

- o **Delivery**: Acceleration of neural networks' SoftMax layer for both training and inference in Pytorch. Achieved baseline accuracy using only the optimal number of bits required for classification i.e., $\lceil \log_2 c \rceil$ where c is the number of classes
- o Technical Skills: Pytorch, Python, Customized training of neural networks
- Research and Collaboration: Ideal bit-allocation for training different layers of nns, batch-norm quantization, impact of weights distributional assumptions on quantization, exploding/vanishing gradients, binarization of transformers

University of Waterloo

Waterloo, CA

Postdoctoral (at CS dept.) and Graduate Researcher (at C& O dept.)

May 2016 - Feb 2022

- Research: Conducted research in stochastic optimization and graph neural networks
- Technical Skills: Numerical Analysis, Optimization, Statistics, Machine learning, Python, CPU/GPU, C++, MATLAB, Parallel processing, Dask, Spark, Code performance optimization, Object oriented programming
- Tutorial Sessions: Numerical Computation, Linear Algebra, Introduction to Optimization, Fundamental of Optimization, Semi-definite Programming, Portfolio Optimization, Deterministic OR Models

Young Scholars Club (Seasonal - Part Time)

Tehran, IR

Mathematical Olympiad Coach

Sep 2006 - May 2016

- o Teaching: Algebraic Combinatorics, Analytic Number Theory, Probability Theory, and Algebra
- o **Problem Solving**: Held challenging problem solving (e.g., Putnam) sessions so students develop their math. skills
- Problem Design: Part of problem designing committee for Iranian mathematical Olympiad exams²

EDUCATION

University of Waterloo

Waterloo, CA

PhD in Mathematical Optimization at the department of Combinatorics & Optimization

May 2016 - Apr 2021

Thesis: Simple Termination Criteria for Stochastic Gradient Descent Algorithm

Sharif University of Technology

Tehran, IR

Bachelor's and Master's degree in Fundamental Mathematics

Sept 2006 - July 2012

I studied Algebraic Geometry and Number Theory during this time.

SELECTED HONORS AND AWARDS

Iranian Mathematical Olympiad (Silver Medal, 2005)³

¹I started learning quantitative finance at CIBC and have continued my studies independently since starting a non-quant position

 $^{^2}e.g.$, I created the following: Does there exists two functions $f,g:\mathbb{R}\to\mathbb{R}$ s.t. $|f(x)-f(y)|+|g(x)-g(y)|>1, \forall x\neq y$?

 $^{^3\}mathrm{Olympiad}$ medals are awarded annually to 40 out of 320,000 competing students